Guide to the Donald Horowitz Collection on Ethnic Riots
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Donald Horowitz collection on ethnic riots
1903-2000
MS 1968
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
(5 boxes)
The collection consists of published materials including articles, government reports and inquiries, newspaper articles, as well as academic presentations and correspondence regarding international incidents of ethnic strife, riots, and uprisings. The materials were collected by Donald L. Horowitz when researching his book, The Deadly Ethnic Riot (2001). They document events from circa 1929 to 2000 in Africa, South Asia, Southeast Asia, Asia Minor and Central Asia, East Asia, and Europe, with ethnic conflicts in Africa and Asia most represented.
Horowitz, Donald L., 1939-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of published materials including articles, government reports and inquiries, newspaper articles, as well as academic presentations and correspondence regarding international incidents of ethnic strife, riots, and uprisings. The materials were collected by Donald L. Horowitz when researching his book, The Deadly Ethnic Riot (2001). They document events from circa 1929 to 2000 in Africa, South Asia, Southeast Asia, Asia Minor and Central Asia, East Asia, and Europe, with ethnic conflicts in Africa and Asia most represented.
Arrangement
The collection is organized alphabetically by country, region, or topic.
Biographical / Historical
Donald L. Horowitz was born on June 27, 1939, in New York City. He was educated at Syracuse University (A.B., 1969 and LL.B., 1961) and Harvard University (LL.M., 1962, M.A., 1965, and Ph.D., 1968). Following various appointments with the federal judiciary and research institutions in international affairs, he began teaching at Duke University in 1980 where he was the Charles S. Murphy Professor from 1988 to 1993 and since 1994, the James B. Duke Professor of Law and Political Science. Horowitz has also held visiting academic appointments at the University of Chicago Law School, Central European University, and Wolfson College, Cambridge University. He has served as an international consultant to foreign governments on issues related to elections and electoral systems, ethnic violence, and federalism. Among his published works are two books that focus on ethnic strife: Ethnic Groups in Conflict (1985) and The Deadly Ethnic Riot (2001).
Culture conflict; Ethnic relations; Ethnicity; Race riots; Social conflict; Horowitz, Donald L., 1939-
- Inventory
  - Ahmedabad, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Algeria, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aligarh/Moradabad, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Armenia: riots, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Assam, 1950-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5-15)
  - Assam: Immigration, Ethnic Conflict and Political Turmoil, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Aurangabad, Bihar (1987): Yadavs vs. Rajputs (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Azerbaijan, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Baku, Azerbaijan, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Baku, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bangladesh, Anti-Bihari Riots, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Belfast, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bijnor, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bombay (Shiv Sena), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bombay (anti-Muslim), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bombay, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Brazzaville, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Britain: riots, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Burma, 1930-1997 (Box 1, Folder 29-35)
  - Burma (Prome), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Burma (Rangoon v. Rohingya), 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Burundi, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 38-41)
  - Calcutta (parts I-II), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Cambodia, 1970-1994 (Box 1, Folder 44-46)
  - Chad, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - China, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Congo (K), (Nicolai, etc) Part I, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Congo (K), (Chome) Part II, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Congo - Brazzaville, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Congo (B), Undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Cyprus, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Delhi, 1974, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
  - Delhi Riots, 1974-1989 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Delhi-Meerut, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 57-58)
  - Djibouti (Issas v. Afars Gadaburst), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Durban, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Egypt, Khanka, 1972 November (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Egypt, Cairo, 1981 June (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Egypt, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Ethiopia, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Ferozabad, U.P., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Fiji, Suva, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Former Soviet Union: riots, Undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Gabon, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Gabon - Cameroon, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Georgia (against Pontic Greeks and Ossetians), 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Germany, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Ghana, 1981-1995 (Box 2, Folder 72-76)
  - Ghana, Nigeria, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Gujarat, Part I (articles from New Age, Economic and Political Weekly, etc.), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Gujarat, Part II and III (microfiche articles), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 79-80)
  - Gujarat, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Guyana, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Haryana, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Hong Kong: riots, Undated (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Hyderabad, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Hyderabad, Andhra Pradesh, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Hyderabad (anti-Muslims), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - India, Hindu - Muslim to 1950, 1905-1950 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - India (Gujarat-Baroda), (Hindu-Moslem Gujarat), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - India-Riots-Ayodhya, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - India: Hindu-Muslim, various, 1968-1997 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - India, Nadia, W. Benegal, 1979 June (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - India (1979 in Palacode; 1980 in Sasaram), Undated (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - India (anti-Sikh), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - India: riots, Undated (Box 3, Folder 95-96)
  - Indonesia, 1963-1997 (Box 3, Folder 97-101)
  - Indonesia Riots, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Iran (Kurds and Turks), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Iran (Sistanis), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Ivory Coast, 1958, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Jainpur-Suchetpur (U.P.), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Kabilya, Algeria, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Karachi, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Karachi-Hyderabad, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Karachi (Sunni-Shi'ite riots), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Karachi, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 111-112)
  - Hyderabad and Karachi, Pakistan, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Karachi, File - Horowitz, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Karimgant: riots, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Horowitz- Kashmir file, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Kazakhstan, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Kenya, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Kenya [Luo-Nubian], 1995 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Kirgizia (OSH), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Kirgizstan, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Kishinev, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Kokrajhar, Assam (Bodo-Bengali Muslim), 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Kosovo, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 124-125)
  - Liberia, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Liberia, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Lithuanian: riots, Undated (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Lucknow, 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Madagascar, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Madura, Undated (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Malaysia, 1945, 1964, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Malaysia - Part I, 1945-1967 (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Malaysia - Part II, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Manipur, India, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Mau Nath Bhanjan, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Mauritania - Senegal, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Mauritania, Undated (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Mauritius: riots-Boutique, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Mauritius, 1968, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Medan, Indonesia, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Meerut, 1968, 1982, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 142-144)
  - Moldova, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Moradabad, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Muncar, East Java, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Nigeria, 1945, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 148-149)
  - Nigeria - Part I (Melsom, O'Connell, etc), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Nigeria - Part II, (Anber, Onugu, etc), 1966 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Nigeria (Christian - Muslim), 1980s (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Nigeria, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 153-154)
  - Nigeria, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Northern Ireland, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Odessa, 1905, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Orissa (anti-Marwari), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Pakistan (Punjab), 1974 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Pakistan, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Palestine, 1929, pre-1947, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Papua New Guinea, Bougainville, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Philippines, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Philippines - Part II Christians v. Muslims (magazine articles), 1973-1983 (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Punjab (Calcutta): Sikh-Hindu, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Punjab, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Punjab - Part I (Dominguez article), 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Punjab - Part II (newspaper articles, etc), 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Punjab - Part III (periodicals, etc), 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 169)
  - Quetta, Balochistan, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Ranchi, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - Rawalpindi, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 172)
  - Rhodesia, 1960, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 173)
  - Riots (General), Undated (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Riots and elections - Part I (newspapers, etc.), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Riots and elections - Part II (periodicals, etc.), 1969 (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Romania (Tirgu Mures), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Rwanda (Hutu v. Tutsi), 1992 (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Sabah, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 179)
  - Sierra Leone: Poro - for chapter 2, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 180)
  - Singapore, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 181)
  - Singapore, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 182)
  - Singapore, Haja Maideen, Nadra Tragedy, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 183)
  - South Africa, 1949, 1976, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 184-186)
  - South Africa (Zulu - Xhosa), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 187)
  - Sri Lanka, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 188)
  - Sri Lanka (Ceylon), 1956, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 189)
  - Sri Lanka, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 190-192)
  - Sri Lanka (newspaper articles), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 193)
  - Sri Lanka (Tamil refugees, etc), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 194)
  - Sri Lanka, 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 195-196)
  - Sri Lanka - Part I (Dissanayka - Marga Institute), Undated (Box 5, Folder 197)
  - Sri Lanka - Part II (newspaper articles), 1983 (Box 5, Folder 198)
  - Sri Lanka (Tamil - Moor), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 199)
  - Sri Lanka, 1989-1990, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 200-201)
  - Sri Lanka (commercial disturbances), Undated (Box 5, Folder 202)
  - Sudan, 1955, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 203)
  - Sukabumi, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 204)
  - Sumgait, Armenia, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 205)
  - Sumgait, Azerbaijan, 1988 February-March (Box 5, Folder 206-207)
  - Syria, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 208)
  - Taiwan, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 209)
  - Tajikistan, Dushanbe, 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 210)
  - Thailand, 1945, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - Zaire, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 212)